A Guide to the James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1923-1974
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1923-1974
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6626-e
4800 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Library acquired these papers from James Kilpatrick on 13 Dec 1974.
Scope and Content Information
The bulk of the collection consists of James J. Kilpatrick's correspondence, 1973-74, with readers of his column and his radio and television audience. Chief topics are Spiro Agnew, the U.S. Constitution, consumer protection, crime, the economy, education, Daniel Ellsburg, energy, job safety, the law and prisons, F.D.A. regulations, Nixon, pornography, religion in the schools, the Watergate scandal, welfare and women's liberation, and personal correspondence from William F. Buckley and Harry F. Byrd, Sr. Also included are scripts for his ABC and CBC news commentaries, WTOP news commentaries, CBS "Point and Counterpoint", and CBS "60 minutes," as well as many speeches. Kilpatrick's financial papers, his engagement calendars, reviews of his books and notes from the 1968 and 1972 presidential campaigns constitute the remainder of the collection.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1964-1973 (Box 1-8)
  - William F. Buckley 1964-1967, 2 folders; ca. 105 items (Box 1)
  - Harry F. Byrd 1963-1966, 23 items (Box 1)
  - World Wide Lecture Bureau, Inc. 1964-1973, ca. 77 items (Box 1)
  - World Book Encyclopedia 1970, ca. 26 items (Box 1)
  - Abortion 1973, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Spiro Agnew 1973-1974, ca. 80 items (Box 1)
  - Agronsky 1973-1974, ca. 51 items (Box 1)
  - Amnesty 1973, ca. 50 items (Box 1)
  - Automobiles 1973, ca. 32 items (Box 2)
  - Bicentennial 1973-1974, ca. 40 items (Box 2)
  - Books 1973, 18 items (Box 2)
  - Business 1973, ca. 40 items (Box 2)
  - Communism 1973, ca. 42 items (Box 2)
  - Conservatism 1973-1974, 2 folders; ca. 156 items (Box 2)
  - Constitution 1973, ca. 105 items (Box 2)
  - Consumerism 1973, ca. 56 items (Box 3)
  - Crime 1972-1973, ca. 34 items (Box 3)
  - Defense 1973, 10 items (Box 3)
  - Economy 1973, 43 items (Box 3)
  - Education 1973, 2 folders; ca. 185 items (Box 3)
  - Daniel Ellsburg 1973, ca. 54 items (Box 3)
  - Energy 1973, folder 1; ca. 102 items (Box 3)
  - Energy 1973-1974, folder 2; ca. 84 items (Box 4)
  - Environment 1973, ca. 62 items (Box 4)
  - Foreign Affairs 1973, ca. 80 items (Box 4)
  - Greece 1973, 14 items (Box 4)
  - The Kennedys 1973, 32 items (Box 4)
  - Labor 1973-1974, 27 items (Box 4)
  - Law 1973, folder 1; ca. 84 items (Box 4)
  - Law 1973-1974, folder 2; ca. 95 items (Box 5)
  - George McGovern 1972, 4 items (Box 5)
  - Medical Care 1973, 2 folders; ca. 140 items (Box 5)
  - Metric Systems 1973, 4 items (Box 5)
  - Richard M. Nixon 1972-1973, 3 folders; ca. 283 items (Box 5)
  - Richard M. Nixon 1973, 2 folders; ca. 192 items (Box 6)
  - Pitts-Lee Case 1973, 12 items (Box 6)
  - Poetry 1973, 2 items (Box 6)
  - Politics 1973, 2 folders; ca. 152 items (Box 6)
  - Pornography 1972-1973, ca. 35 items (Box 6)
  - Press 1973, ca. 88 items (Box 6)
  - Press 1973, 2 folders; ca. 210 items (Box 7)
  - Privacy 1973, 6 items (Box 7)
  - Race 1972-1973, ca. 40 items (Box 7)
  - Ronald Reagan 1973, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Religion 1972-1973, ca. 98 items (Box 7)
  - Rhodesia 1973-1974, 5 items (Box 7)
  - Social Security 1973, 9 items (Box 7)
  - Stamps 1973, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Tobacco 1973-1974, 10 items (Box 7)
  - Transportation 1973, 8 items (Box 7)
  - United Nations 1973, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Watergate 1973, ca. 110 items (Box 7)
  - Watergate 1973, 4 folders; ca. 373 items (Box 8)
  - Welfare 1972-1973, ca. 50 items (Box 8)
  - Women's Lib 1973, 11 items (Box 8)
- Research notes and draft of an article re: Marcus Arnheiter 1968, ca. 60 items (Box 8)
- Articles on the U.S. Supreme Court for the National Review 1970-1973, 5 items (Box 9)
- Photograph of James J. Kilpatrick 2 Aug 1941, 1 item (Box 9)
- State Fair of Virginia Ribbon Badge 1964, 1 item (Box 9)
- Newsclippings re Kilpatrick 1966-1967, 6 items (Box 9)
- "The Saga of James J. Kilpatrick" Washington Post16 Sep 1973, 2 items (Box 9)
- "James J. Kilpatrick," by Morton Kondracke, WashingtonianOct 1973, TMs (photocopy) (Box 9)
- Correspondence with K.L. Endres and a term paper, "James J. Kilpatrick: a Conservative at Work" 1973, 4 items (Box 9)
- Book reviews by Kilpatrick 1957-1963, ca. 125 items (Box 9)
- Indexes for Kilpatrick's Commentaries on ABC, CBC, CBS, and WTOP, compiled 1973 1969-1972, 4 items (Box 9)
- Kilpatrick's ABC commentaries and correspondence 1968-1970, ca. 133 items (Box 9)
- Kilpatrick's Canadian Broadcasting Corporation Commentaries 1969-1971, 7 items (Box 9)
- Kilpatrick's CBS "60 Minutes," "Point-Counterpoint" Commentaries 1970-1972, 38 items (Box 9)
- Kilpatrick's CBS "60 Minutes," "Point-Counterpoint" Commentaries with Nicholas Von Hoffman 1973, 32 items (Box 9)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's WTOP Commentaries, with a record of WTOP tapings 1969, ca. 93 items (Box 10)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's WTOP Commentaries 1970-1971, 4 folders; ca. 233 items (Box 10)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's WTOP Commentaries 1972, ca. 110 items (Box 11)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's WETA Commentaries 1972, 3 items (Box 11)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Calendar Diary 1965, 1 item (Box 11)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Calendar Diary 1966, 1 item (Box 11)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Calendar Diaries 1967-1969, 3 items (Box 11)
- Notes covering the Nixon Campaign May 1968, 8 items (Box 12)
- Campaign notebooks of J.J. Kilpatrick re: Wallace, McGovern, and Humphrey 1972, 3 items (Box 12)
- ""Four Years After, A Backward Look at the School Cases," by J.J. Kilpatrick 1958, TMs (Box 12)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's notes for various speeches 1961-1964, n.d., 28 items (Box 12)
- "The Case for States' Rights," Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick 1961, TMs (Box 12)
- "View from a Southern Exposure," Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick 1963, TMs (photocopy) (Box 12)
- "Conversation on Virginia," Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick before the Virginia Congressional Dinner of the Va. State Chamber of Commerce 1965-1967, 3 items (Box 12)
- "The Topless Bathing Suit, and Other Footnotes to American History" Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick 19 Apr 1968, 3 items (Box 12)
- Speech on the Press and Courts, by J.J. Kilpatrick, given to the Oklahoma Press Association 19 Nov 1968, TMsS (Box 12)
- Notes for speech on U.S. Supreme Court for the Clearwater Executive Club, Clearwater, Fla. 26 Jan 1969, TMs (Box 12)
- "A Slightly Elliptical View of 'The Crisis of our Cities,'" Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick before the Association of Senate Press Secretaries 30 Jan 1969, TMs (Box 12)
- Speech, by J.J. Kilpatrick, on Liberty and Order to the Illinois Manufacturers' Association 20 Mar 1969, TMs (Box 12)
- "A Conservative View of the Urban Crisis," Speech by J.J. Kilpatrick at the Auburn Conference on International Affairs 1 Apr 1969, TMs (Box 12)
- "The Crime Rate and How it Afrects Small Business; the Alternatives for Action," Speech, by [J.J.K.] before the National Federation of Independent Business 17 May 1971, TMs (photocopy) (Box 12)
- "My Time is Your Time," Address by J.J. Kilpatrick 5 Jun 1971, 3 items (Box 12)
- Debate with Karl Hess at T.C.U.: Old Right vs New Left 5 Oct 1971, 2 items (Box 12)
- Meet the Press: McGovern, Humphrey, Jackson & Chisholm, printed brochure 9 Jul 1972, 1 item (Box 12)
- Notes for speech on Freedom of the Press, given in New Orleans 27 Sep 1972, TMs (Box 12)
- Tapes by J.J. Kilpatrick for NET-TV and CBS-TV (Speed 3 3/4) re: Amnesty and Week at end 23 Mar, 22 May 1973, 2 items (Box 12)
- Assets of Blanche Hawley 1923-1933, 1967, 14 items (Box 12)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Income Taxes 1943-1964, ca. 120 items (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous receipts and papers taken from J.J. Kilpatrick's 1947 Account Book 1947, 7 items (Box 13)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Account Book 1947, 7 items (Box 13)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Account Book 1948-1950, ca. 42 items (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous receipts and papers taken from J.J. Kilpatrick's 1951 Account Book 1951-1954, 7 items (Box 13)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Account Book 1951, 1 item (Box 13)
- J.J. KIlpatrick's Account Book 1951-1957, 1 item (Box 13)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Account Book 1958-1962, 1 item (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous receipts and papers taken from J.J. Kilpatrick's 1958-1961 Account Book 1958-1961, 19 items (Box 13)
- J.J. Kilpatrick's Account Book 1964-1966, 1 item (Box 13)
- Receipts taken from J.J. Kilpatrick's 1964-1966 Account Book 1964, 2 items (Box 13)
- Perlstein vs. Kilpatrick, et al 1964, 12 items (Box 13)
- Indentures, correspondence, and receipts re: 905 G Street, S.E. 1966-1968, ca. 55 items (Box 13)